"Oh, Corrina."
"Oh, Corrina.
"Why are the letters from you so short?"
Kenapa surat darimu begitu singkat?
"Like Eupolis the astrol… astrologer,
Seperti Eupolis, ahli astro… astrolog,
you throw my heart into disarray."
hatiku berkecamuk karenamu.
"The gold of Idas so fades."
Emas Ida begitu pudar.
-"The craftsman of Gallonius…" -Just stop already.
- Kerajinan Gallonius…" - Cukup.
I've told you there is no need to read any more.
Sudah kubilang tak perlu kau teruskan.
Um, is something the matter?
Apa ada masalah?
You're done here.
Tugasmu selesai.
Just leave already.
Sana pergi.
I apologize.
Maafkan aku.
Have I offended you in some way?
Apa aku sudah menyinggung?
Someone without proper Latin pronunciation
Orang yang tak bisa mengeja bahasa Latin
has no right to read books to me.
tak pantas membacakan buku untukku.
I apologize. I will be more careful.
Maaf. Aku akan belajar lagi.
I'm telling you to leave.
Sudah kubilang pergi.
FRIEDRICH EMMANUEL SCHOOL OF MUNICH UNIVERSITY
SEKOLAH FRIEDRICH EMMANUEL UNIVERSITAS MÜNCHEN
You were scolded pretty harshly back at the mansion.
Tadi kau diomeli habis-habisan di rumahnya.
Chin up, business management major Karl Neuman.
Bersemangatlah, Karl Neuman mahasiswa jurusan manajemen bisnis.
What?
Apa?
How do you know about me? Who are you?
Bagaimana kau tahu aku? Kau siapa?
I'm Lotte Frank, a cultural anthropology major.
Aku Lotte Frank, mahasiswi jurusan antropologi budaya.
Do you also work part-time reading books for that man?
Kau juga kerja paruh waktu membaca buku untuk orang itu?
No, I take care of him.
Tidak, aku merawatnya.
He only lets male students read books to him.
Dia cuma izinkan mahasiswa membacakan buku.
You're the Tuesday boy.
Kau piket Selasa.
On the other days, other students
Beda hari, beda mahasiswa
read books for that nearly blind man.
yang bacakan buku untuk pria yang nyaris tunanetra itu.
Hey, what do you think about him?
Apa pendapatmu tentangnya?
That mysterious man of wealth, Hans Georg Schuwald.
Pria kaya misterius, Hans Georg Schuwald.
Not really sure.
Entahlah.
I only jumped at the job because the pay was good.
Aku kerja sampingan di sana karena bayarannya bagus.
Have you heard all the rumors about him?
Sudah tahu rumor soal dia, belum?
With one call from the estate,
Tinggal telepon dari rumahnya,
he can freely control the stocks of any company in Germany.
dia bisa mengendalikan saham perusahaan Jerman mana pun.
He's known as the Howard Hughes of Bavaria.
Dia dikenal sebagai Howard Hughes-nya Bayern.
He has no family or anyone close to him.
Dia tak punya keluarga atau kerabat,
Yet his fortune keeps growing.
tapi kekayaannya terus bertambah.
What do you think he plans to do with that money?
Menurutmu untuk apa uangnya?
Not sure.
Entahlah.
But there's an even bigger mystery.
Tapi ada misteri yang lebih besar.
Another one of his aliases is the Vampire of Bavaria.
Julukan dia yang lain adalah Vampir dari Bayern.
Vampire?
Vampir?
When the bell rings at 2:00 a.m.,
Saat bel berbunyi pukul 02.00,
he rides a coffin-like car accompanied by his butler
dia naik mobil mirip peti mati ditemani pelayannya
and heads to town in the dead of night.
dan pergi ke kota di tengah malam.
It's like a scene out of a gothic horror story.
Seperti adegan di kisah horor gotik.
Isn't he just taking a walk?
Mungkin cuma jalan-jalan.
I'll figure out soon enough if it's just a walk or not.
Kita akan tahu kalau memang cuma jalan-jalan.
Figure out? Are you…
Akan tahu? Apa kau…
It's for my research thesis.
Ini untuk tesis penelitianku.
"The Psychology of Bavarian Financiers from the Middle Ages and Today."
"Psikologi Pemodal Bayern dari Abad Pertengahan dan Modern."
He'll definitely be a great sample.
Dia sampel yang bagus.
So, while you were at it, you looked into me too, huh?
Jadi, kau tahu soal aku karena mengorek soal pria itu, ya?
I only looked up your name and major.
Aku cuma mengorek nama dan jurusanmu.
Well, don't be upset that you got yelled at by Schuwald, okay?
Jangan sedih karena dimarahi Schuwald, ya?
He says awful things to the other students too.
Dia juga sering mengomeli mahasiswa lain.
Yeah, I'm used to being hit and yelled at.
Ya, aku sudah terbiasa dipukul dan dimarahi.
You're used to it?
Terbiasa?
Yeah, I went through a lot, moving from one foster home to another.
Ya, aku sering berpindah rumah asuh.
Oh right, you didn't attend one of the local preparatory high schools.
Benar juga, kau tak masuk ke SMA daerah sini.
So you actually did look into me.
Ternyata kau memang mengorek tentangku.
I see.
Begitu, ya.
You don't have parents.
Kau tak punya orang tua.
Actually, I enrolled in Munich University because I thought I could meet my mother.
Sebenarnya aku masuk Universitas München karena kukira bisa bertemu ibuku.
Your mother is in Munich?
Ibumu di München?
So, did you meet her?
Ketemu, tidak?
No. It doesn't matter now.
Tidak. Sudah tak penting lagi.
What? Why?
Apa? Kenapa?
But you're finally near her.
Padahal, sudah di dekatnya.
You know her name, right?
Kau tahu namanya, 'kan?
Yeah.
Ya.
What is her name?
Siapa namanya?
I told you it doesn't matter.
Sudah kubilang itu tak penting.
Just tell me.
Katakan saja.
Once I'm interested, I figure things out one way or another.
Kalau sudah tertarik, pasti akan kutemukan jawabannya.
It's Margot.
Margot.
Margot Langer.
Margot Langer.
If you know that much, you can find her right away.
Kalau tahu namanya, pasti akan segera ketemu.
Go see her.
Ayo temui dia.
She'll be thrilled.
Ibumu pasti senang.
Like I said, it doesn't matter now.
Seperti kubilang, sudah tak penting.
Margot Langer…
Margot Langer.
No way!
Tak mungkin.
"The sprint of the chestnut-colored horse
"Berpacunya kuda cokelat itu
gathered thunderclaps in my blood."
menjadi gemuruh dalam darahku.
"It caused great waves…"
Gelombang begitu besar."
I can't bear to listen any more.
Aku sudah muak.
I only love that which is beautiful.
Aku hanya menyukai keindahan.
I can't bear to listen anymore.
Aku muak mendengar itu.
Why didn't you tell me something so important?
Kenapa hal sepenting itu tak disampaikan?
I looked up your mother.
Aku mencari tahu soal ibumu.
I don't know what to say.
Aku tak bisa berkata-kata…
Didn't I tell you it doesn't matter?
Sudah kubilang, itu tak penting.
Karl, is there any way I can be of help to you?
Karl, apa ada yang bisa kubantu?
Thanks, but it's fine.
Terima kasih, tak perlu.
Karl…
Karl.
Lotte.
Lotte.
About Hans Schuwald's movements at night,
Soal jalan-jalan malam Hans Schuwald…
-you said you'd figure him out, right? -What?
- Kau akan cari tahu, 'kan? - Apa?
Can I come with you?
Apa aku boleh ikut?
Yes, of course!
Ya, tentu saja!
That'd be reassuring for me too.
Itu akan menenangkanku juga.
I'm telling the truth!
Sungguh!
It's the Supernatural Phenomenon Club's biggest scoop ever!
Ini berita terbesar bagi Klub Fenomena Supernatural!
I have my doubts.
Aku tak yakin.
But really, there's no doubt this poem was written in 1502
Pokoknya, tak diragukan lagi puisi ini ditulis tahun 1502
by Bishop Gropius, one of the university founders.
oleh Uskup Gropius, salah satu pendiri universitas.
This one section is the key.
Kuncinya di paragraf ini.
"In the second-to-last of the fullest years,
"Di tahun penuh yang kedua sebelum terakhir,
the Thursday boy will visit this place."
pemuda hari Kamis akan datang.
"The books shall be enveloped in flame,
Buku-buku akan dilahap api
and the entire world shall be enveloped in sadness."
dan dunia akan diliputi kesedihan."
So what?
Terus, kenapa?
Don't you get it?
Kau tak paham?
See here? "The second-to-last of the fullest years."
Lihat ini. "Tahun penuh yang kedua sebelum terakhir."
That's 1996.
Maksudnya 1996.
In other words, this year.
Berarti, tahun ini.
How so?
Tahu dari mana?
"Fullest years" is referring to leap years.
"Tahun penuh" maksudnya tahun kabisat.
The only leap years this century are this year and 2000.
Tahun kabisat yang tersisa di abad ini adalah tahun ini dan 2000.
"…visit this place. The books shall be enveloped in flame."
"…akan datang. Buku-buku akan dilahap api."
The part with the books in this place is implying this university will burn.
Bagian soal buku berarti kampus ini akan terbakar.
Then what is "the Thursday boy"?
Lalu, apa itu "pemuda hari Kamis"?
The word donnerstag, meaning Thursday, comes from donner.
Donnerstag, artinya Kamis, berasal dari kata donner.
In other words, thunder!
Donner berarti petir!
It's the god of thunder!
Dewa petir!
That's a big stretch.
Ngawur sekali.
This isn't funny!
Tidak lucu!
It's our next newsletter's feature!
Ini berita eksklusif nawala kita!
I'm fine with putting it in there,
Mau diberitakan tak masalah,
but who'd believe
tapi siapa yang percaya
that a god of destruction would come to this university?
kalau dewa kehancuran datang ke universitas ini?
The Vampire of Bavaria? Yeah, right.
Mananya vampir dari Bayern?
This is the truth after we chased after his mysterious loitering?
Inikah fakta di balik jalan-jalannya yang misterius?
How disappointing.
Mengecewakan sekali.
Quiet. He's coming.
Sut. Dia datang.
This is stupid.
Konyol.
I'm leaving.
Aku mau pulang.
Okay, get home safely.
Ya, hati-hati.
What?
Apa?
I'm going to go take a look.
Aku mau mengeceknya.
Go where?
Ke mana?
Hey, let's stop this.
Hei, kita pulang saja.
Yeah, this isn't somewhere to bring a girl.
Ya, tak pantas mengajak cewek kemari.
You should leave.
Kau pulang saja.
"I only love that which is beautiful."
"Aku hanya menyukai keindahan."
What?
Apa?
I want to know
Aku ingin tahu
just how despicable this man is.
seberapa hina pria itu.
It's open.
Tidak dikunci.
If you're looking for women, you're in the wrong place.
Jika mencari perempuan, kau salah tempat.
I've already retired long ago.
Aku sudah lama pensiun.
Who are you?
Kau siapa?
When you visit someone, you should introduce yourself first.
Yang mendatangi seharusnya berkenalan lebih dulu.
I'm Margot Langer.
Aku Margot Langer.
What?
Apa?
You look like you're a student.
Sepertinya kalian mahasiswa, ya?
Yes, I am.
Ya.
I do part-time work at Hans Schuwald's home.
Aku bekerja paruh waktu di rumah Hans Schuwald.
And why are you here?
Kenapa kau kemari?
I want to know why Mr. Hans Schuwald comes here.
Aku ingin tahu kenapa Pak Hans Schuwald kemari.
He comes here for fun.
Untuk bersenang-senang.
Or that's what I'd like to say.
Aku ingin bilang begitu,
But apparently he can't get it up anymore.
tapi tampaknya "barang"-nya tak bisa bangun lagi.
He comes to give me money.
Dia datang memberiku uang.
What?
Apa?
It's only natural.
Wajar saja.
When I went to him and told him my name,
Saat kusebutkan namaku,
he started crying and apologized.
tiba-tiba dia menangis dan minta maaf.
After all, he threw me away like trash after making me birth a child.
Dia mencampakkanku bagai sampah setelah memaksaku melahirkan.
Karl, could it be that you're Hans Schuwald's child?
Karl, mungkinkah kau anak Hans Schuwald?
-But-- -You're lying.
- Tapi… - Bohong.
You're…
Kau…
You're not Margot Langer.
Kau bukan Margot Langer.
Yeah, it was in the papers a year ago.
Ya, ada di koran setahun lalu.
"Former prostitute…"
"Mantan PSK…"
"Former prostitute Margot Langer was killed."
"Mantan PSK, Margot Langer, dibunuh.
"Culprit still at large."
Pelaku belum ditemukan."
His mother is already dead.
Ibunya sudah meninggal.
You took advantage of that, posing as my mother, Margot Langer,
Kau memanfaatkan itu, menyamar sebagai ibuku, Margot Langer,
taking away large sums of money from Hans Schuwald.
lalu memeras uang dari Hans Schuwald.
He knows too.
Dia juga tahu itu.
He pays me, knowing that I'm not the real one.
Dia tahu aku bukan yang asli, tapi dia tetap membayarku.
He knows the real Margot he should pay no longer exists,
Dia tahu Margot yang asli tak bisa lagi menerima uangnya,
so this is his way of atonement.
jadi ini cara dia menebus dosanya.
Money, money, and money.
Uang, uang, dan uang.
To a man who has only lived with money, this is the only way he knows.
Bagi orang yang hanya memiliki uang, cuma ini cara yang dia tahu.
He speaks like he's above everyone, but people are all the same.
Bicaranya sangat angkuh, tapi semua manusia sama saja.
You could go up to the old geezer, say you're his son,
Kau bisa bilang ke orang tua itu kalau kau putranya,
and get that enormous fortune of his.
dan kau bisa dapatkan kekayaannya.
What's your point?
Apa maksudmu?
You're calling me a liar,
Kau menyebutku pembohong,
but I'm not too sure about you either.
tapi aku juga ragu kau jujur.
There's another person
Ada satu orang lagi
who's calling himself his son.
yang mengaku sebagai putranya.
-What?!
- Apa?
He came here just like you did and said the exact same thing.
Dia datang ke sini dan menceritakan hal yang sama.
No way.
Tak mungkin.
It can't be.
Itu mustahil.
It's a lie.
Bohong.
That guy was lying.
Orang itu bohong.
I don't know which of you is the liar.
Entah siapa dari kalian yang bohong.
You both look like fakes to me though.
Tapi bagiku kalian sama-sama gadungan.
Who is that guy?
Siapa orang itu?
He's just like you.
Dia sepertimu.
You all have your own day of the week when you read books to Schuwald, right?
Masing-masing dari kalian punya jadwal untuk membacakan buku ke Schuwald, 'kan?
That boy was one of them too.
Pemuda itu juga salah satunya.
Yes, I believe it was
Ya, seingatku,
the Thursday boy.
dia yang piket Kamis.
Why didn't you tell her you're the real one?
Kenapa kau tak bilang kau putra kandungnya?
I…
Aku…
I've moved between many foster homes, one after another.
Aku sering berpindah dari rumah asuh ke rumah asuh lain.
So of course, I've been through a lot.
Banyak hal yang sudah kuhadapi.
But my current foster parents have been really good to me.
Tapi orang tua asuhku sekarang sangat baik kepadaku.
I could never thank them enough.
Aku sangat berutang budi.
That's why I wanted to try meeting my real parents.
Itu sebabnya aku ingin menemui orang tua kandungku.
By learning how despicable my real father is,
Dengan mengetahui betapa hinanya ayah kandungku,
I thought I could learn to truly love my current foster parents.
kupikir aku bisa memperdalam rasa sayang ke orang tua asuhku.
But that was it.
Itu saja tujuanku.
Have you seen the Thursday boy before?
Kau pernah bertemu yang piket Kamis?
Thursdays are my days off, so…
Hari Kamis aku libur.
But I've gone to get something I forgot before.
Tapi aku pernah kembali saat mengambil barang…
You've seen him before? What's he like?
Kau pernah lihat? Seperti apa dia?
What's he like?
Seperti apa dia?
He was blond, with very pretty facial features.
Dia berambut pirang dan wajahnya tampan.
MONDAY
SENIN
Who is this Thursday boy?
Siapa yang piket Kamis itu?
There is a man pretending to be me at this university.
Ada pria yang pura-pura menjadi aku di universitas ini.
Listen, Karl.
Dengar, Karl.
Listen to what your mother has to say.
Dengarkan baik-baik ibumu ini.
Take this money and ride train number five.
Bawa uang ini dan naik kereta nomor lima.
When you get off at the eighth station, an old lady named Marta will be there.
Saat kau turun di stasiun ke-8, ada ibu-ibu bernama Marta.
What about you, Mom?
Ibu bagaimana?
I told you. I can't go with you.
Ibu tidak bisa ikut.
Are the police chasing you?
Apa Ibu dicari polisi?
-I'll stay with you too. -No.
- Aku mau ikut Ibu. - Jangan.
If you stay with me, you'll be put into an orphanage here.
Jika bersama Ibu, kau akan dimasukkan ke panti asuhan.
If you stay, you'll be called a prostitute's boy.
Di sini, kau akan dipanggil anak pelacur.
Go now. Hurry.
Cepat berangkat.
-What about Dad? -What?
- Ayah bagaimana? - Apa?
My dad's a person named Hans Georg Schuwald, right?
Ayahku Hans Georg Schuwald, 'kan?
Who told you that?
Kau dengar dari siapa?
Vera from across the street was saying it.
Tante Vera di seberang jalan.
He's super rich, right?
Dia kaya raya, 'kan?
She said that I was thrown away by my dad.
Dia bilang aku dibuang oleh Ayah.
You weren't thrown away.
Kau tak dibuang.
Then I'll go stay with Dad.
Kalau begitu, aku tinggal bersama Ayah.
You can't right now.
Sekarang tak bisa.
Then when can I?
Kapan bolehnya?
When you grow up.
Kalau sudah besar,
If you still want to meet him as an adult.
jika kau masih ingin menemuinya.
But you mustn't want anything.
Tapi jangan harapkan apa pun.
Don't resent him if he treats you coldly.
Jangan benci meski sikapnya dingin.
Why?
Kenapa?
Because I don't resent him.
Karena Ibu tak membencinya.
Take this with you.
Bawalah ini.
This was from your dad when you were born.
Ini pemberian ayahmu saat kau lahir.
Karl, I figured it out.
Karl, aku tahu.
I found out who the Thursday boy is.
Aku tahu siapa yang piket Kamis.
What?
Apa?
His name is Edmund Fahren. He's in the Faculty of Literature.
Namanya Edmund Fahren. Dia mahasiswa Fakultas Sastra.
He's definitely reading books for Schuwald on Thursdays.
Dia membacakan buku untuk Schuwald di hari Kamis.
Edmund Fahren…
Edmund Fahren.
He should be here.
Di sini.
The lecture in this classroom just ended.
Kebetulan kuliah di kelas ini selesai.
Hey.
Hei.
We're looking for Edmund Fahren.
Kami mencari Edmund Fahren.
What? Oh, him.
Apa? Oh.
Is Edmund here?
Edmund ada di sini?
Edmund?
Edmund?
He wasn't here today.
Hari ini dia absen.
You heard him.
Begitu katanya.
Oh, really?
Begitukah?
That was unfortunate.
Sayang sekali.
But it's only a matter of time.
Tinggal masalah waktu.
We'll grab that fraud by the neck soon enough.
Ayo segera tangkap penipu itu.
You're the one who will inherit Schuwald's enormous fortune.
Kau yang akan mewarisi harta melimpah Schuwald.
It's not about that.
Bukan soal itu.
What?
Apa?
I don't care about the inheritance.
Aku tak peduli soal warisan.
But…
Tapi…
He can squeeze out as much of Schuwald's money as he wants.
Dia bebas memeras uang Schuwald sebanyak apa pun.
But…
Tapi…
But?
Tapi?
But that student named Edmund Fahren
Murid bernama Edmund Fahren itu
is saying he's my mother's son. I can't let that slide.
mengaku sebagai putra ibuku. Aku tak terima.
TUESDAY
"Saat pakaianmu yang bercorak bunga berkibar ditiup angin,
a mockingbird was calling out to me in my heart."
burung memanggil dari dalam hatiku."
You didn't say anything today, Mr. Schuwald.
Tumben kau tak berkomentar, Pak Schuwald.
What?
Apa?
I have yelled at you so many times. Why haven't you quit?
Aku sudah sering membentakmu. Kenapa kau belum mundur?
Is it because the pay is nice?
Karena bayarannya tinggi?
Of course not.
Tidak.
That's not why I'm here.
Bukan itu alasanku kemari.
Is money all you can talk about?
Kau cuma bisa membahas soal uang?
It's just as you say.
Kau benar.
Who are your parents?
Orang tuamu siapa?
I was raised by foster parents.
Aku dibesarkan oleh orang tua asuhku.
Is that so?
Begitu, ya.
Sorry for my rude question.
Maaf, jika menyinggung.
Don't you want to meet your real parents?
Apa kau tak ingin bertemu orang tua kandungmu?
To be honest…
Sejujurnya,
I…
aku…
It seems the boy who appeared this time is the real deal.
Sepertinya yang kali ini datang benar-benar tulus.
He's not after my money.
Dia tak mengincar uangku.
"He"?
"Dia"?
No, I was just talking to myself.
Tidak, aku melantur.
You can go home now.
Kau boleh pulang.
Oh, and also…
Lalu…
Your Latin…
Pelafalan bahasa Latinmu
has gotten better.
makin baik.
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
WEDNESDAY
RABU
It seems Edmund Fahren is absent today too.
Tampaknya Edmund Fahren absen lagi.
Geez, I bet he's just lying in bed with a cold.
Ya ampun, paling dia terbaring karena flu.
We don't have to rush. Tomorrow is Thursday.
Tak perlu buru-buru. Besok hari Kamis.
He'll show up to his job at Schuwald's.
Dia akan datang ke rumah Schuwald.
Oh, I see.
Begitu rupanya.
You'll rip off his disguise right in front of Schuwald.
Kau akan bongkar identitasnya di hadapan Schuwald.
Let's do it.
Ayo.
Let's totally destroy him.
Kita jebak dia.
THURSDAY
KAMIS
He's not showing up.
Dia tak datang.
Almost an hour has passed.
Sudah lewat hampir satu jam.
If he has a cold, we could confront him while he's bedridden.
Kalau dia flu, kita labrak saja mumpung dia terbaring.
Hey.
Hei.
In that case, how about we barge into his lodgings?
Bagaimana kalau kita datangi apartemennya?
You've even looked into Fahren's address?
Kau juga mencari tahu alamat Fahren?
204…
204…
204.
204.
Here it is.
Ini dia.
Come on.
Ayo.
FRIDAY
JUMAT
This complicates things.
Jadi masalah besar, ya?
Everyone on campus is talking about Edmund Fahren.
Semua orang di kampus membicarakan Edmund Fahren.
I can't believe he committed suicide.
Tak disangka dia bunuh diri.
The school paper has his suicide note in it too, right?
Koran sekolah juga memuat pesan terakhirnya.
"I can no longer deceive others."
"Aku tak bisa lagi membohongi orang lain."
This must mean…
Pasti ini berarti…
Yeah.
Ya.
Pretending to be Schuwald's son and getting close to him
Mendekati dan pura-pura menjadi putra Schuwald
must have been eating at his conscience.
pasti mengusik hati nuraninya.
If he was so troubled that he'd die,
Jika merasa bersalah hingga bunuh diri,
he shouldn't have done it in the first place.
harusnya dari awal tak dilakukan.
Lotte, yesterday must've been tough.
Lotte, pasti kemarin berat, ya.
Yeah, it was.
Ya, benar.
The police kept questioning me about the situation all day.
Seharian aku terus dimintai keterangan.
I have the day off today from the book reading job.
Hari ini aku libur dari kerja membaca buku.
Schuwald was incredibly depressed.
Pak Schuwald sangat terpuruk.
Oh, Karl, let me introduce you.
Karl, kenalkan.
This is the Friday guy.
Dia yang piket Jumat.
Nice to meet you.
Salam kenal.
Hi, I'm Karl Neuman from the economics department.
Hai, aku Karl Neuman dari fakultas ekonomi.
I'm Johan Liebert from the law department.
Aku Johan Liebert dari fakultas hukum.